Attached to this lecture here you'll find the starting project you can see here.
Bu dersin ekinde burada grebileceiniz balang projesini bulabilirsiniz.
I just started it with npm start, it uses create react project. I didn't edit it to use css modules, instead
Ben yalnzca UM ile baladm kullandklar balanglar kullandm Riak projesini yarattm ve CSSA modllerini dosyalar olarak
I just import css files so that they affect the project globally
CSA'y ithal etmek yerine dzenleyerek projeyi global olarak etkiledi.
but that doesn't pose an issue here.
Fakat burada bir sorun tekil etmiyor.
And I got a couple of containers or one container and a couple of components.
Ve birka konteynr veya bir konteynerim ve bir ka komponentim var.
As you can see at the example of the full post component here which is responsible for rendering this
Burada bu blmn oluturulmasndan sorumlu olan tam posta bileeni rneinde grebileceiniz gibi
path here, I even have class based components here as components because I plan on adding some local
burada snf temelli bileenler de bileen olarak sahibim nk baz yerel durumlar ve baz yaam
state and some lifecycle hooks to these components which is why I set them up like this.
dngs bileenlerini bu bileenlere eklemeyi planlyorum; bu nedenle ayarladm bileen onlar byle seviyorum.
Still I only have one component which will distribute some properties down to other components,
Yine de yalnzca baz zellikleri Obert bileenlerine datacak bir bileene sahibim.
this is the root page you could say which should render some posts at the top then a full post with
Bu, stte baz postalar oluturacaklarn syleyebilecein kk sayfadr, daha sonra bir postayla ilgili baz
some details about a post we clicked on and the area for creating a new post. You can see all these features
ayrntlar ieren tam bir yazya ve yeni bir yaz oluturmak iin alana, bu
here on that page.
sayfadaki tm bu zellikleri grebilirsiniz.
Now I do have some dummy content here because I want to load that post data from a server
imdi burada baz kukla ierik var, nk bu post verilerini bir sunucudan yklemek istiyorum.
and for that we're not going to use a real server,
Ve bunun iin gerek bir sunucu kullanmayacaz.
we will do that though in the next module when we apply some HTTP functionality to our course project.
Bunu bir sonraki modlde ders projemize baz HTP ilevsellii uyguladmzda yapacaz.
But here I will use JSONPlaceholder which you can find at jsonplaceholder.typeicode.com
u. kukla verilere ya da bazen verileri saklamaya benzetmek iin orada bir ey saklamazsnz.
which simply is a backend, a RESTful API backend which you typically use as I explained in the last
Ancak burada bulabileceiniz baz yer tutucu kullanacam, baz yer tutucu nokta
lecture, where you can send requests to to fetch some dummy data or to simulate storing sometimes data
tr kodlar nokta geribildirimde yalnzca bazlar getirmek iin istek gnderebileceiniz son konferansta akladm
there though you won't actually store something on that server
gibi kullandnz dinlendirici bir API arka
of course, it's just faking some data but exactly what we need for learning how to send HTTP
Elbette sadece baz verileri taklit etmekle birlikte, isteklerin tekrarlanmas iin yan nasl gnderileceini renmek iin
requests.
ihtiyacmz olan ey.
For example, you can send a request to that URL here, a GET request and you will get an array of javascript
rnein daha nce bir GET isteine babanza bir istek gnderebilirsiniz ve kukla mesajlarn javascript
object of dummy posts.
nesnesinin bir dizisini alrsnz.
And this actually is what I want to start with
Ve aslnda bu benimle balamak istediim ey.
so we will start with that in the next lecture
Bir sonraki konumada bununla balayacaz.
but we of course need some way of sending these ajax requests.
Ancak elbette DS Ajax isteklerini gndermenin bir yoluna ihtiyacmz var.
And here you have basically two options,
Ve burada iki seeneiniz var.
Javascript of course has the XMLHttpRequest object,
Elbette Javascript'in talep nesnesine Exham l h vardr.
this object here. With that, you can construct your own Ajax requests and send them to a specific URL
Bu nesneyle, kendi Ajax isteklerini oluturabilir ve bunlar belirli bir L'ye gnderebilir ve
and handle the response.
yant idare edebilirsiniz.
Nothing wrong with that since react is just about writing javascript everywhere,
Yeniden hareket her yerde javascript yazmaktan tr l bir ey deil.
you can of course use all the javascript features including XMLHttpRequest but writing and configuring
Elbette Exham L.'yi de ieren tm javascript zelliklerini kullanabilirsiniz. H. yazlmas ve yaplandrlmas olduka zahmetlidir.
requests with that object manually is quite cumbersome.
TDP istei ancak bu nesneyle elle yaplan isteklerin
So the second option is to use package, a third party library which makes that easier
Bu nedenle ikinci seenek, paketi daha kolay hale getiren bir nc parti kitapl kullanmaktr.
and for that I recommend using axios. Axios is a third party javascript library which you can add
Ve bunun iin herhangi bir javascript projesine ekleyebileceiniz bir nc parti javascript kitapl olarak X
to any javascript project,
yl x yl kullanmanz neririm.
it's not connected to react at all
Hi tepki vermeye bal deildir.
but of course it fits nicely into react because it's well javascript, and the axios page here on Github
Ancak tabii ki EC'ye uyuyor nk iyi javascript ve DXi get have on page sayfas paket hakknda daha
is a good starting point to learn more about this package,
fazla bilgi edinmek iin iyi bir balang noktas.
I will of course walk you for some of its core features in this module though.
Tabii ki bu modlde temel zelliklerinden bazlar iin sizi arayacam.
But again this is not something strongly connected to react, axios can be used in any javascript code.
Ancak yine de, eski U'ya tepki gstermek iin gl bir ekilde baladm bir ey deil. S. herhangi bir javascript kodunda kullanlabilir.
So let's install axios in this lecture already and then get started using it in the next lecture. To
Bu dersin banda X-ists'i ykleyelim ve sonra X'i yklemek iin bir sonraki derste kullanmaya
install axios,
balayalm.
I will quit my development server with CTRL+C and then run npm install axios --save
Evet, gelitirme sunucumunu C denetleyicisiyle hzlandracam ve daha sonra NPM install ex-U'yu altracam. S. izgi izgi tm maaza
to also store an entry in the package.json file.
kaydetmek ve komu dosya paketi girmek.
This will download and store the package and with that, we can start using it in the next lecture to
Bu, paketi indirip depolayacak ve bir sonraki konferansta baz yaynlar almak zere
fetch some posts. So let me restart development server with npm start and I'll then see you in the next lecture
kullanmaya balayabiliriz, bylece NPM balama ile gelitirme sunucusunu yeniden balatabilir ve ardndan baz yaynlar indirip oradan
to download some posts and output them there.
ktracak bir sonraki derste siz balayabiliriz.